Finding Aid for the Baruch Lumet Papers, 1955-1983 LSC.1451
UCLA Library Special Collections
Baruch Lumet papers
1955-1983
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lumet, Baruch
LSC.1451
2.8 linear feet (6 doc boxes, 1 flat box)
Baruch Lumet (1898-1992) was an actor in theater and movies, and an author. He wrote and acted on New York City radio programs (1932-42), made his Broadway debut in The Chinese Nightingale (1934), toured North America in his one-man show, Monotheatre Varieties (1939-46), wrote Three Steps Down (1946) and Once upon a Tailor (1953), and appeared in films and television programs. From 1953 to 1960, Lumet served as director of the Dallas Institute of Performing Arts and the Knox Street Theater, Dallas, Texas (1953-60). His son is director Sidney Lumet. The collection consists of Lumet's personal papers relating to his career in the theater. Includes photographs, manuscripts, clippings, scripts, and videotapes, including his KCET television special, Portrait of My People.
Restrictions on Access
Stored off-site. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Baruch Lumet, 1983.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942333423606533
Biography
Lumet was born on September 16, 1898 in Warsaw, Poland; graduated from the Warsaw Academy of Dramatic and Musical Arts, 1918; made his debut as an actor there in the same year, and appeared in London (1920-21), and in various productions of Maurice Schwartz's Yiddish Art Theater in New York City (1926-31); wrote and acted on New York City radio programs (1932-42); made his Broadway debut in The Chinese Nightingale (1934), and toured North America in his one-man show, Monotheatre Varieties (1939-46); wrote Three Steps Down (1946) and Once upon a Tailor (1953); appeared in the films One third of a nation (1939), The interns (1962), and Adventures of a Young Man (1962); appeared on television programs, including Studio One, Kraft Television Theater, Playhouse 90, The Untouchables, and Alfred Hitchcock Presents; served as director of the Dallas Institute of Performing Arts and the Knox Street Theater, Dallas, Texas (1953-60). His son is director Sidney Lumet.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of the personal papers of Baruch Lumet, relating to his career in the theater as an actor and a writer. Includes photographs, manuscripts, clippings, scripts, and videotapes, including his KCET television special, Portrait of my people.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Scripts and Manuscripts Written by Lumet
Series 2: Theater Career
Dramatists -- United States -- Archives.; Actors -- United States -- Archives; Lumet, Baruch -- Archives
- Series 1: Scripts and Manuscripts Written by Lumet, 1955-1983
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title of the work.
  Scope and Content
  This series consists of scripts and manuscripts written by Lumet. There are many versions of Lumet's play Once Upon a Tailor, as well as a handwritten draft and typed manuscript of Lumet's autobiography Who Am I?.
  - As the Twig Is Bent…: Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autumn Fever: Script, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autumn Fever: Script, related material, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daylight Saving Time: Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Dybbuk: Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fishke the Lame: Script, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Matanah (The Gift): Proposal for television program, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Translation from Yiddish to English, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Translation from English to Yiddish, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Ephemera, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Broadway script, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Original handwritten script in Yiddish, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Script, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Scripts, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Once Upon a Tailor: Script, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poor Man's Luck: Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Purim Play: Handwritten notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - So You Wanna Be an Actor?: Synopsis, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - So You Wanna Be an Actor?: Manuscript, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Spring in September, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Three Steps Down: Script, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Written by Baruch Lumet and Bert Child. Baruch Lumet's first play in English.
  - The White Cloud: Script, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Alternate title is The Modern Golem. In a handwritten note, Lumet writes "Written before Hitler was in power."
  - Who Am I?: Manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Who Am I?: Handwritten autobiography draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-3, Box 3, Folder 7-10)
  - Misc.: Manuscripts and notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Theater Career, 1955-1983
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  This series consists of materials related to Lumet's theater career, both as an actor and as director of the Dallas Institute of Performing Arts. It includes photographs, clippings, correspondence, and sound recordings.
  - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, newspaper clippings: Jayne Mansfield, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Founding documents: Dallas Institute of Performing Arts, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clipping: Sidney Lumet, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings: Portraits of My People reviews, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs: Sidney Lumet at ten years old, 1930s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs: "Dallas Productions in My Theater" Scrapbook, 1951-1960 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: The Verdict directed by Sidney Lumet, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, ephemera, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Programs: Dallas Institute of Performing Arts, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Promotional material: Once Upon a Tailor, undated (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Publication: by Baruch Lumet in Yiddish, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sound recordings from Lumet's productions, undated (Box 4)
    11 reel-to-reel tapes.
    Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Misc., 1950s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 8-9)